A Guide to the Additional Papers of John Page Elliott, 1803-1996
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of John Page Elliott 1803-1996
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2433-ai
This collection consists of ca. 1000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift on 1998 October 5.
Scope and Content Information
Papers of John Page Elliott consist primarily of research material collected for his biography of Philip St. George Cocke including correspondence with family members and research institutions, copies of original documents from the University of Virginia and other institutions and some genealogical information.
The collection also contains original Cocke family letters, manuscripts, certificates and photographs, including a daguerreotype of John Hartwell Cocke, two daguerreotypes of "Uncle John Cocke," a tintype, a hand painted miniature, and four photographs of various Cocke and Shields family members including Betty Burwell Page Cocke.
Original items include an 1814 letter from George Blow to John Hartwell Cocke regarding clothing for soldiers in Cocke's brigade; Lucy Cocke's travel journal to the springs, 1822; an 1851 letter from A. B. Girrard to John Hartwell Cocke on the Eppes family; a catalog of books at Belmead, 1838, in the hand of Philip St. George Cocke; a document, 1804, signed by Virginia governor John Page; and Philip St. George Cocke's West Point diploma, 1832.
Research topics include a proposed school of agriculture at the University of Virginia; architecture, Belmead and Alexander Jackson Davis; the battle of First Mannasses; Cocke family genealogy; politics; slavery; and the Virginia Military Institue.
Correspondents include Betty Cocke, Douglas Southall Freeman and Jennings C. Wise.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence re the Cocke family 1930-1995, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Douglas Southall Freeman 1930-1938 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with the University of Virginia 1959-1992 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Jennings C. Wise 1958-1961 (Box 1)
- Topical
  - Agriculture 1856-1858 (Box 1)
  - Agriculture 1965-1986, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Appendices and Exhibits n.d. (Box 1)
  - Architecture 1984-1994 (Box 1)
  - Belmead: Architecture of Alexander Jackson Davis 1846, 1980-1992 (Box 1)
  - Belmead: Correspondence 1977-1995 (Box 1)
  - Belmead: Manuscripts 1951-1995 (Box 1)
  - Belmead: Manuscripts for the Biography 1990s (Box 1)
  - Belmead: Miscellaneous 1848-1980, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Biographical Data on Philip St. George Cocke 1859, 1986-1991 (Box 1)
  - Civil War 1902-1990, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Cocke Family Records 1870-1872, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Early Homes 1990s (Box 2)
  - Education and Religion 1990s (Box 2)
  - Estate 1860-1887, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Genealogy of the Cocke family 1927-1992, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Marriage 1832-1834, 1990s (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Research Notes n.d. (Box 2)
  - Photographs and Portraits 1834-1859, 1979, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Photographs and Portraits: Correspondence 1978-1987 (Box 2)
  - Preface and Dedication n.d. (Box 2)
  - Slavery and Politics 1990s (Box 3)
  - Transcripts and Copies of Correspondence of John Bowdoin Cocke 1851-1886, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Transcripts and Copies of Correspondence of Philip St. George Cocke 1833-1862 (Box 3)
  - Transcripts and Copies of Correspondence of the Cocke family 1803-1901, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Tributes to Philip St. George Cocke 1861-1862 (Box 3)
  - Tributes to Philip St. George Cocke 1915-1992, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Virginia Military Institute 1846-1861 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Military Institute 1974-1992, n.d. (Box 3)
- Original Cocke Family Material
  - Certification of justice of the peace of Henrico County, signed by the Governor of Virginia, John Page 1804 Oct 7 (Box 3)
  - George Blow to General [John Hartwell] Cocke 1814 Oct 5 (Box 3)
  - Travel Journal kept by Lucy Cocke, and including a discourse on the six essential properties possessed by bodies 1822 Aug-Sep (Box 3)
  - Catalogue of Books in the Library at Four Mile Tree now at Belmead 1838 (Box 3)
  - A. B. Girrard to John Hartwell Cocke 1851 Aug 22 (Box 3)
  - Courtney [Bowdoin Cocke] to "My dear Brother" 18[ ] Apr 7 (Box 3)
  - William Horner Cocke to Bettie Page Cocke 1927 Nov 21 (Box 3)
  - G. S. Stephens to Lucy Cocke Elliott 1931 Feb 17 (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Cocke and Shields family members n.d. (Box 3)
  - Portrait of Philip St. George Cocke n.d. (Box 3)
  - Daguerreotype of John Hartwell Cocke, in old age n.d. (Box Mini-tray)
  - Daguerreotype of "Uncle John Cocke," in uniform n.d. (Box Mini-tray)
  - Daguerreotype of "Uncle John Cocke," young man n.d. (Box Mini-tray)
  - Cased photograph of unidentified gentleman in uniform n.d. (Box Mini-tray)
  - Cased tintype of unidentified couple n.d. (Box Mini-tray)
  - Hand-painted miniature of unidentified gentleman n.d. (Box Mini-tray)
  - West Point diploma of Philip St. George Cocke, signed by all of the faculty 1832 (Box Oversize Box M-19)
  - (tattered) (Box Oversize Box M-19)
  - Shriner certificates for John Bowdoin Cocke 1922 (Box Oversize Box M-19)
  - Color drawing of Bettie Burwell (Page) Cocke n.d. (Box Oversize Box M-19)
  - Photograph of Bettie Burwell (Page) Cocke n.d. (Box Oversize Box M-19)